<document title="Data types">
  In one respect, Smyle is much closer to traditional relational databases than
  to object oriented databases: it basically stores just data, not objects.
  However, unlike relational databases, Smyle supports sophisticated structured data types.
  And it offers a source code generator that makes these data types appear almost
  like "real" objects.
  <p/>
  
  (When I say "objects", I'm talking about entities that encapsulate their data and
  communicate with the
  outside world through messages. Data records, on the other hand, are manipulated by
  directly accessing their internal fields; there are no messages, and there is no
  encapsulation.)
  <p/>

  A Smyle data <i>store</i> consists of a number of independent <i>tables</i>. Each
  table is basically an ordered set of <i>rows</i>. All rows in one table are of the
  same <i>struct type</i>.
  <p/>
  
  Struct types are defined in a special language, the IDL (Interface Definition Language;
  though it should rather be called Type Definition Language). A struct type consists of
  named, typed fields. A field can be of a basic type (string, long (32 bit), long long (64 bit),
  boolean);
  of another struct type, or of a sequence type. The following IDL example illustrates all
  three variants:
  <p/>
  
  <codeblock>
    struct Address {
      string street;
      string city;
    };
      
    struct Person {
      string name;
      long age;
      Address address;
      sequence&lt;string&gt; titles;
    };
  </codeblock>
  
  After you wrote an IDL file, you use the Smyle code generator to transform it into Java
  classes. You then have objects that you can manipulate very conveniently, e.g. like this:
  
  <codeblock>
    Person john = new Person("John", 55, new Address("Main Road", "Birmingham"))
      .titlesAdd("Ph. D.")
      .titlesAdd("Professor");
      
    System.out.println("Name: "+john.name);
    System.out.println("Full details: "+john);
  </codeblock>

</document>
